please
this is a suitor called a wanderer
so a certain brahmana approaches the
blessed one and says to him
master gautama it is said a directly
visible dhamma a directly visible dumber
i think you translated that sandico
as a verifiable so we could say a
verifiable a verifiable dump in what way is the
a verifiable dump in what way is the
dhamma
verifiable immediate
reachable inviting one to come simple
practical and to be personally
experienced by the discerning by the
discerning and the buddha says brahman
and the buddha says brahman
one excited by lust overcome by lust
with a mind obsessed by it intends for
his own affliction for the affliction of
the affliction of others or for the
affliction of both
and he experiences mental suffering and
dejection and sadness
but when lust is abandoned he does not
intend for his own affliction for the
affliction of others or for the
affliction of both
and he does not experience mental
suffering and sadness
one excited by lust overcome by lust
with mind obsessed by it engages in
misconduct a body speech to mind
but when lust is abandoned he does not
engage in misconduct
one excited by lust overcome by lust
with mind obsessed by it
does not understand as it really is his
own good the good of others or
the good of both but when lust is
abandoned he understands as it really is
his good
the good of others and the good of both
it is in this way
brahman that the dhamma is directly
verifiable and so on with hate and delusion
so the dhamma is directly visible
here and now you don't you don't have to
wait exactly you don't have to wait and you
exactly you don't have to wait and you
don't have to take it on mere faith
alone either because it's not about
like you know the whole the dhamma the
whole nibana the enlightenment the whole
experience of enlightenment it's nothing
other than complete
uprooting of lust aversion and delusion
slash distraction
it's not a mystical experience or some
some great heavenly reward
the only reason you're subject to
suffering misery and everything else
in this life it's lust aversion delusion
and if you remove that in this life you
will not be subjected to those things
anymore and you would see that directly
for yourself
and that's the relief that's the release
that's the enlightenment
that's the quenching of the mind cooling
down and so on all the similarities in
the suttas from ibana
and that is directly verifiable you can
experience it here and now
if you are the discerning one if you
make the effort to discern things
and then obviously apply that
discernment because many like religions or teachers
because many like religions or teachers
even back in the time would be
teaching you one thing or the other with
sort of
you know future results that you kind of
have to take of faith
in a sense of well next life i guarantee
you heavenly rivers like the whole
christianity the heaven the idea of
heaven for example
that is the ultimate reward there are
rewards you get in this life by being
virtuous in honored religions as well but the
in honored religions as well but the
ultimate reward it's what's after
well not in the dhamma the dhamma the
ultimate reward is here and now visible
you cannot be touched by suffering of
any kind it doesn't apply to you anymore
plus there are future rewards sure but
you don't need to worry about that
they will become apparent either through
a practice of
here and now or even if they don't
doesn't matter what is directly
verifiable it's to be known individually by an
it's to be known individually by an
individual who is discerning enough
and obviously who makes enough effort in
that direction and what is that
verifiable thing
is that removal of lust removal of
aversion removal of distraction not perpetuating
removal of distraction not perpetuating
it through the
actions by body speech and mind will
liberate you here and now
visibly you will see it it cannot be
doubted it cannot be shaken it cannot be
taken away
so you you you cannot have a more
immediate proof
and that's what it was like said even
and in one sutra
maybe venerable anand somebody was
asking the buddha
there's another a a person who became
fully enlightened
like you know they enjoy the pleasure of
enlightenment of the pleasure of release
the freedom or does that stay all the
time with them or
or they kind of you know go back to
normal so to speak in terms of they
don't feel that elation anymore of of
the great release and relief
and we said no it doesn't stay you know
you get used to it becomes your norm and
like in mind
but you would re-experience it the joy
of
your freedom of of your release and
relief and cooling down every time you were to
and cooling down every time you were to
encounter things that used to induce
lust aversion or distraction in your
mind so you might accidentally stumble
upon things that used to make you angry
or something
and now you realize there is not just
there's no more anger there's no basis
there's no possibility for
anger or lust or any perturbing of the
mind and that reminds you of how free you are
and that reminds you of how free you are
and you experience
the joy of freedom again every time you
you you these things pop up
but that's that is as i said there's
nothing that can come between you and
that if you have uprooted greater last
if you have uprooted greater last
aversion delusion
so it's the most verifiable thing that
you can access that's why it's reachable
that's why it's sort of encouraging
inviting and so on
yeah no look this i'm not saying like
you must follow me
at the face value and then in 10
lifetimes you'll be rewarded or
something no no
you need to take my teaching of faith in
a sense of you need to take the doctor's
instruction of faith
but soon enough you will see if it's the
right instruction or not if you start
applying it rightly
you should be curing yourself and that
is that's something you cannot doubt
um and that's why the people who did
develop the right view and free
themselves from suffering
in the suttas they they said um like
oh no it's like you know um if if the
whole ball says the buddha was wrong
i know he's right and it wasn't because
of some misguided
fundamentalism or something with
conviction no it's because no i am
literally cured
i cannot suffer on account of his
instruction so the world is wrong if they say that
so the world is wrong if they say that
he that that's not right
because i have verified it for myself
i'm incapable of experiencing dukkha
again because of uprooting of last diversion
because of uprooting of last diversion
delusion
so it's the world is wrong then if they
disagree with that
that's it not like oh i fight the whole
world and i defend my teacher out of my
faith no no
i have directly verified it for myself
and it's just
it just cannot be doubted it cannot be
taken away that's why it's the
unshakeable liberation that the suitors
will refer to
and the dhamma is practical it's a
practical teaching
exactly like the only way to see whether
the dharma is
what the dharma says it is where the
demo will result in freedom from
suffering liberation is to apply it
to actually do it and that's that's an
important thing because if it remains an
abstract theory exactly if you are not it cannot
theory exactly if you are not it cannot
be practically applying it
applying yourself you're not doing it
and if you're not doing it you cannot
verify it and if you cannot verify it's
not a dumb